<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lively character of the malignant partie: wherein their persons, who they are; their actions, what they have already done, and do daily further attempt; with their intentions, at what ends they ayme, are sufficiently set forth, fully described, and plainly evidenced to the indifferent judgement of any ordinary man, who hath had but a reasonable view of the strange passages of these later times. By one who cordially affects his Soveriagne, and really respects the Parliament: which illustrious and renowned senate, hath (for the safetie of the King, and presevation of the kingdome) resolved upon the question, that in this malignant partie, they may not, must not, will not, cannot confide.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88379</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E240_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2828</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872194</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872194</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88379)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 41:E240[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lively character of the malignant partie: wherein their persons, who they are; their actions, what they have already done, and do daily further attempt; with their intentions, at what ends they ayme, are sufficiently set forth, fully described, and plainly evidenced to the indifferent judgement of any ordinary man, who hath had but a reasonable view of the strange passages of these later times. By one who cordially affects his Soveriagne, and really respects the Parliament: which illustrious and renowned senate, hath (for the safetie of the King, and presevation of the kingdome) resolved upon the question, that in this malignant partie, they may not, must not, will not, cannot confide.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Published and printed in the yeare of feares and jealousies, plots, projects, and policies, designes, dangers, and discoveries. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "October ye 7th 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158280:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIVELY CHARACTER OF THE MALIGNANT PARTIE: WHEREIN Their Perſons, who they are; their Actions, what they have already done, and do daily further at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; with their Intentions, at what ends they ayme, are ſufficiently ſet forth, fully deſcribed, and plainly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced to the indifferent Judgement of any ordinary man, who hath had but a reaſonable view of the ſtrange Paſſages of theſe later times.</p>
            <p>By one who cordially affects his Soveraigne, and really reſpects the Parliament: Which illuſtrious and renowned SENATE, hath (for the ſafetie of the King, and preſervation of the Kingdome) Reſolved upon the Queſtion, That in this Malignant Partie, they may not, muſt not, will not, cannot confide.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed and Printed in the yeare of Feares and Jealouſies, plots, projects, and policies, deſignes, dangers, and diſcoveries. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:158280:2"/>
            <head>THE MALIGNANT PARTIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat there is a Malignant Partie, is confeſt of all; but who this Malignant Partie is, that hath generated and ſomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the preſent diſtempers and diſtractions of this now languiſhing Kingdome, <hi>His labor, hoc opus eſt.</hi> In the firſt place, I will demonſtrate who theſe are. According to their common appellation, they are a company of male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent, or ill-affected perſons to the peace of this Church and State: And theſe are ſo many for their multitude, that (like the Devill himſelfe) they may be termed <hi>Legion,</hi> as properly as the wicked man. Theſe <hi>Aegyptian Locusts</hi> ſwarme in every corner of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; the <hi>Hydra</hi> of this Malignant Partie doth daily multiply and is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch an Epidemicall diſeaſe, that like a Leproſie, it hath over-ſpread the whole body of this Nation. I ſhall onely nominate the chiefe of them. who have been (and are ſtill deſigned) maine Actors in the fearefull Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of this lamentable Age.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Sceane, ye may behold if ye pleaſe) Papiſts, perſons popiſhly inclined, their Accomplices and Adherents, all the members of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Hierarchie, as Jeſuites (the incendiaries of all Chriſtendome) and others of that Romiſh faction; They are alwayes chriſtie after bloud, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting rapine, torture, oppreſſion, and crueltie; Their machinations have been miſchievous, and their deſignes are ſtill deſtructive. They have ever plotted the promoting of hortid warre, as the onely meanes to advance the Catholike cauſe, whoſe end and marke they ayme at, is to recover and re-eſtabliſh the Romiſh Religion here within this Kingdome. Was not the warre with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the inſurrection there two yeares agoe, incited and fomented by them? Was not the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> the laſt yeare, begun, framed, and contrived by them? And is not this unnaturall, civill warre, now in <hi>England,</hi> occaſioned and maintained by them? But they who have inſtigated his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie to ſuch a barbarous and bloudy warre againſt his Parliament and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (which is of a confounding nature to the three Kingdomes at once) what are they but moſt deſperate Traytors to their King and Countrey, moſt execrable Vipers to God and his Church? <hi>they hatch Cockairioe egges, and weave the Spiders web; their workes are workes of iniquitie, and the act of violence is in their hands; their feet run to evill, and they haſt to ſhed innocent bloud; their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158280:2"/>
thoughts are thoughts of iniquitie; wasting and deſtruction is in their paths; the way of peace they know not; and there is no judgement in their goings. They have made them crooked paths; whoſoever goeth therein, ſhall not know peace,</hi> Iſa. 59. 5. <hi>Their throate is an open Sepulchre, with their tongues they have uſed deceit; the poyſon of Aſpes is under their lips; their mouth is full of curſing and bitterneſſe; their feet are ſwift to ſhed bloud; deſtruction and miſery are in their wayes, and the way of peace they have not knowne; there is no feare of God before their eyes,</hi> Rom. 3. 13. They have for many yeares together had an impious deſigne, to alter Religion, to defile the puritie thereof, and to introduce Popery, ſuperſtition, ignorance, the onely way to an arbitrary and tyrannicall Government, and to change the frame and conſtitution of this Government both in Church and State: The Maſter-piece of all their Stratagems (a new engine which they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented to heighten the deſtruction of this Kingdome) was to prevaile with his Majeſtie by that Proclamation to leavie forces againſt the Parliament, and the Kings loyall Subjects, by that meanes to put this Land into a certain combuſtion, inevitable confuſion by civill warre, and perpetuall ſlavery upon the ſurviving part of a then miſerable Kingdome; For if the power of the ſword ſhould come once into their hands (which God forbid) nothing can be then expected, but the moſt wretched ruine and deſolation of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the ſavage maſſacre of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>In the next Scean, enters upon the Stage, to be preſented to your view, the Prelaticall Partie, who have acted a great part in this Tragicall Story of the Malignant Partie. Theſe Popiſh Prelates have corrupted the pure fountaine rather then they would be depreſſed in power; They have brought various innovations into our Church, ſundry alterations into our Liturgie and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, (contrary to the Act of Parliament, whereby the Booke of Common Prayer is eſtabliſhed) vaine Ceremonies, Altars, and many ſtrange (never before heard of) doctrines into our Church, to make us more conſonant to the Church of Rome. Amongſt theſe ye may (if ye pleaſe) take notice of <hi>Laudles Will</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and wretched <hi>Wren</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> both fellow-priſoners in the Tower. To theſe may be added (as a Malignant Partie) all Arminians, an ambitious, diſſolute, and male contented Clergie, corrupt and ſcandalous Miniſters, (their creatures) Delinquents obnoxious to the Juſtice of Parliament; who are ſo farre from being <hi>Paſtores,</hi> that they are altogether <hi>Impoſtores;</hi> not Paſtors, but Impoſtors: Some of them are ſuperſtitiouſly corrupt in their judgements, holding and teaching ſtrange Doctrines; others of them ambitious of preferment; many of them conſcious and guiltie of groſſe and foule crimes; all of them male contented with the Parliament, and their proceedings, and ſo vitiated with idleneſſe, eaſe, and plentie, with the curſed love of lucre and covetouſneſſe, that they would be glad with all their hearts, to ſee the Parliament diſſolved, hoping thereby to recover what they have loſt, or at leaſt to hold faſt what they have got. They make no conſcience to ſtarve the ſoules of their flocke, ſo they may pamper their own bodies.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:158280:3"/>
            <p>The third Scene, containes great Perſonages, part of the Nobilitie and Gentry, that either feare reformation, or elſe ſeeke to lay the foundation of their owne honour and preferment, in the very ruine of the Kingdome. They have a long time lived in a diſſolute way of libertie, without reſtraint of their ſenſuall pleaſures, and therefore are now unwilling to admit of ſuch Reformation, the Parliament in diſcharge of their dutie and conſcience, thinke expedient ſhould be impoſed upon them. Theſe being temerarious, raſh, and unviſed in their attempts and actions, (though Proteſtants, if of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Religion) have endeavour'd to bury the happineſſe of this Kingdome in the downfall and overthrow of the great Counſell thereof. Their precedent intentions (to deſtroy the Parliament, and with it the whole Kingdome) are manifeſted and clearely evidenced by their ſubſequent actions, in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>running ſeverall Counties, compelling the Trained Bands, executing the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall Commiſſion of Array, enforcing them to come in and joyne with them, or diſarming them, and putting their Armes into the hands of lewd and deſperate perſons, thereby turning the Armes of the Kingdome againſt the Kingdome: So that by this meanes all we have, all that is neare and deare unto us, our Eſtates, Lawes, Liberties, and lives, are in danger; nay, that which is the life of our lives, our Religion is in danger; the Kings ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, his royall progeny, and his whole Kingdome by this means is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: For who knowes not, that his Majeſtie is at this time circled and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded, environed as it were by thoſe, who carry him upon his owne ruine, and the deſtruction of his Kingdome, by fomenting and cheriſhing this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and illegall warre againſt his owne people. This Malignant Partie of the Nobilitie, gather unto them the decayed Gentry of ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, who have by prodigalitie, riot, exceſſe, and horſe-races, run their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors eſtates out of breath, and thinke hereby to recuperate them, for they conceive civill warre to be the beſt way ſuddenly to raiſe their fortunes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to their diſcents; and therefore what care they (being many of them neceſſitous Courtiers, and giddy brain'd as they are) to ſatisfie the appetite of their deſire, and the inſatiate thirſt of their ambition, though they ſacrifice a whole Kingdome, delighting to behold their native Countrey ſuffer in the martyrdome of a civill warre. The end that this Malignant Partie doth tend to, is the deſtruction of the preſent Parliament, in it all future Parliaments, and together with them, the alteration of Religion, the ſubverſion of the Lawes of this Kingdome, with the utter abolition of the juſt liberties of the Subjects, and the finall extirpation of the rightfull priviledges of Parliament. They would have all ſubject to will and power, and betray their Countrey to ſerve the Court. 'Tis evident by their love (or rather indeed inveterate hatred) they beare to this preſent Parliament, that they have combined to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, and with it the whole Kingdome. The maſter-piece of their machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations they ayme at, is to be Maſters of our Religion and Liberties, to make us ſlaves, in altering the government of this Kingdom, and reducing it to the ſad condition of ſome other Countreys, which are nor governed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158280:3"/>
and ſo conſequently not by Laws, but by the will of the Prince, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe who are about him, who of late have ſtudied to poſſeſſe the world of an abſolute and unlimited power in Princes, ſo that <hi>Voluntas Regis, is Lex populi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Scene in this Tragedie of the Malignant Party, conſiſts of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents to the Parliament, and Fugitives from the Parliament. Theſe for the moſt part have had their dependance, countenance and encouragement from the Court, where they have flatter'd and ſeduced the King, calumniated and traduced his Councell, abuſed and injured his people. They have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to undermine the Peace of the Kingdom; and their conſtant practiſe hath been to ſet at variance not onely the Princes of ſeverall Nations, but each Kingdom againſt it ſelf, dividing betwixt Prince and people, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſing ſubject againſt ſubject, that ſo they might with more facility accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their impious intentions in our diviſions. They have invited and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the enemies of our Religion, and the State in forrain parts, to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting and acting of their evill deſignes and determinations towards us. Theſe perſons are guilty, not Parliament-proof but ſuch as fear the Juſtice of that high and Honorable Aſſembly in the due execution of Laws againſt them, for the evils and miſchiefs the Common-wealth hath ſuſtained and ſuffered by them; therefore to ſecure themſelves from condigne puniſhment, they are willing to put themſelves under the Kings protection, and under the ſpecious (but unjuſt) pretence of defending the Kings Right and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, to engage themſelves, their lives and fortunes in a bloody warre; thereby to ſet the whole Kingdom in a generall combuſtion. Theſe are the Enemies to the peace of this Kingdom, and juſtly to be ſuſpected to favour the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland.</hi> They have often attempted to fetch in fotrain forces to invade us, and provided great ſupplies of Ammunition beyond Seas to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us. Their complying, contriving and plotting with Papiſts, Atheiſts, Run-awayes, and other notorious Delinquents, are not onely evidences of their deſignes, but do firmly teſtifie that they have been viſible Actors in them. Such a one was the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> who at firſt perſwaded the King to retire himſelf into ſome ſtrong place, and in the mean time promiſed to do his Majeſtie ſervice abroad, having procured ſtore of Arms, with which he came in the ſhip called, <hi>The Providence.</hi> I could nominate more of that party, but I now will not; for there is none ſo great a peregrine in our Iſrael, as is ignorant who they are.</p>
            <p>The fifth contains evill Counſellors, accompanied with corrupted Judges, and ambitious Lawyers, whoſe fears and jealouſies do ariſe out of a guilt of their own vile actions, and juſt fears of their deſerved puniſhment. Theſe are the onely bones of our unhappy diviſions. They have endeavour'd to beget and increaſe diſtruſt and diſaffection between the King, and his Parliament, and his people. Theſe wicked ſpirits of diviſion, and miſchievous inſtruments
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158280:4"/>
of diſſention, have adviſed the King to ſuffer divers unjuſt ſcandals and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations upon his Parliament; And (which aggravates their impietie) theſe evill Counſellors have fixed their diſhonour upon the King, by making his Majeſtie the author of thoſe wicked actions, which are the effects of their own impious counſels. They have adviſed the King to abſent himſelf from his Parliament, whoſe malicious deſignes and practiſes are maskt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed with the falſe colour of their earneſt zeal to vindicate his Majeſties Prerogative from the ſuppoſed oppreſſion of the Parliament. Theſe unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters have often plotted to break the neck of this honorable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie; for which purpoſe they have made ſuch an unpleaſant breach as now is between the King and his great Councell. They have moſt injuriouſly taken all occaſions to multiply groſſe calumnies upon the Houſes of Parliament, to defame, and indeed to arraign the proceedings of both Houſes. Through their deceitfull ſuggeſtions and fraudulent inſinuations, they have engaged the King in deſperate deſignes, and pernicious practiſes: Their private coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell hath incenſed, miſ-informed, and miſ-led his Majeſtie againſt his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Counſell, conſpiring unanimouſly to ruine the very being of Parliament, (which is the fountain of the Law) making it contemptible and of leſſe eſteem then the meaneſt Court, to which all other Courts are inferiour. Hence it is that they have dar'd to caſt upon this Parliament ſuch a charge as is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the nature of that great Councell: They have cauſed a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption in, and obſtruction to the proceedings of Parliament: They have ſtruck at the very being both of the Head and Body, depriving his Majeſtie in his own apprehenſion of their fidelity, and them of his protection, which are the two mutuall bands of Government and ſubjection. By ſecret plots, and open force, they have bred all the late uprores, mutinies and diſturbances in moſt of the Counties of this Kingdom, eſpecially in the Northern parts: The beſieging of <hi>Hull</hi> not long ſince was an egge likewiſe of their hatching. Their plots failing, they have attempted (what no age will ever beleeve, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be as impious as this) to render odious and ſuſpected to the people, the Parliament, which is the onely ſanctuary of their Religion, Laws Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and properties. They have betrayed Church and State, by corrupting the Doctrine and Diſcipline in the one, and ſubverting the Laws and form of Government in the other. Their greateſt influence is upon the Kings Councels; And ſuch is the malignitie of theſe lewd Counſellours, (being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the very height of impudence) that they are not aſhamed to engroſſe and monopolize his Majeſtie to themſelves altogether from his Parliament, by whoſe miſchievous counſels he is wholly diaffected from his Parliaments faithfull advices and counſels, which by the conſtitution of this Realm is his greateſt and beſt Councell. Thus as Chriſt our Lord and Saviour was led aſide into the wilderneſſe to be tempted; ſo <hi>Charles</hi> our Lord and Soveraign is miſ-led from his great Councell, (in which there is ſtrength, prudence and ſafetie) into a wilderneſſe of weakneſſe, errors, and dangers.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:158280:4"/>
            <p>In the ſixt Scene ye may behold with the eye of your Intellect, the Hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurres of the Times, who are call'd the Cavaliers; a name of hatred in the preſent age by their practiſes, and fit to be made a terror to future ages by their puniſhment. Their practiſes in themſelves are as high and as inſolent, as any Subjects ever ventured on. They would (if they could) by armes and violence over-rule the judgement and advice of the Parliament, and by force determine the Queſtions there depending concerning the government of the Kingdom. They have been the chief Actors in the Kingdoms Tragedy, and have preſumed to put that diſhonour and affront upon both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to make them the countenancers of Treaſon; enough to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved all the bands and ſinews of confidence between his Majeſtie and his Parliament. They would (if they durſt come neer it) beſiege <hi>London,</hi> as they lately did <hi>Hull;</hi> and long ago have they ſwallowed up in their thoughts our Religion, Laws, and Liberties; the former by alteration, and the latter by ſubverſion. Amongſt theſe, Captain <hi>Leg</hi> a Delinquent to the Parliament, now a captive faſt enough in the Gatehouſe, endeavour'd <hi>manibus pedibuſque,</hi> in that treaſonable practiſe to bring up the Army againſt the Parliament. Many of theſe incendiaries and fire-brands of combuſtion are the ſame now that were formerly between us and our neighbour Nation, and their deſignes of confuſion of both Nations are the ſame, altring onely the method, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in <hi>England</hi> now with hope to end in <hi>Scotland:</hi> whereas formerly they began there, with purpoſe to end here. Moſt of them are ſuch mercinarie ſword-men, as no Nation nor Age ever expected faith or pietie from; whoſe continuall aſſertious are wounds and blood <hi>(horreſco referens)</hi> I tremble to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it, God damme me, ſink me, or Heavens refuſe 'em, if they be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd upon theſe reſcally Round-heads. Thus <hi>they have God of tentimes in their mouthes. but their hearts are far from him.</hi> As they are criminous in their lives, ſo they are penurious in their eſtates; whoſe good husbandry is to put all upon their backs, and ſhift for their bellies, their lands, houſes and revenues being above in the aire. Though it be true, that many of them are Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men well deſcended, valiant, of good naturall parts, literature, and education, yet for the moſt part men of mean eſtates, odious lives, and deſperate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes: whoſe end is to plunder and pillage whereſoever they come, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves upon the ſpoils of any. This covetous deſire of rapine, to make a prey of people, hath been the great offence committed by our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiers of late, as well as by the Cavaliers, who as they firſt began to practiſe it, ſo they are (I ſuppoſe) more expert at it; for they have neither fear of God, nor reſpect of men before their eyes; but would ſwim through a Sea of blood to their hoped haven; and that they have violently and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally taken away from his Majeſties ſubjects their goods before their faces, 'tis irrefragably evident. To draw all theſe lines to their center; from theſe premiſſes the Inference is this, Theſe grand Apoſtates to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth muſt not expect to be pardoned in this world, till they be diſpatched to the other. I could nominate many more of the malignant party, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158280:5"/>
Pattentees, and other prerogative paraſites. <hi>Humanarum calamitatum mercatores,</hi> as one ingeniouſly ſtyles them, who care not to undo a whole Kingdom, ſo they may get benefit to themſelves. As alſo a giddy-headed multitude in the Land, who are onely Time-ſervers, and (like weather-cocks) will turn at any time to ſerve their own turn; in the mean time by reaſon of ignorance and inability to diſcern what may be the iſſue and ſucceſſe of thoſe beginnings are led on ſimply to their own ruine. But becauſe I will not trench too farre upon the Readers patience, I here deſiſt.</p>
            <p>Thus as in a Map ye may plainly ſee the Malignant Party, who they are, what they have done, and at what they ayme. For the cloſe of all, let us all ſhun their perſons, abſtain from their actions, and hate their intentions. Though they be malignant to the whole Kingdom, yet let not us be male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent to our ſelves; and let us not be ſo uncharitable to them as not to pray for them, that either God would be pleaſed to convert or confound them. Pray we therefore to the King of kings, that he would <hi>take away thoſe wicked ones from before the King, that his Throne may be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe.</hi> To draw this Tract to a period, May they, who have endeavour'd to divide the Head and the Body, (the King and his great Councell, the Parliament) like <hi>Strafford,</hi> have their heads divided from their ſhoulders; or like <hi>Achitophel,</hi> be hang'd up by the neck. This is the wiſh of one, who is neither Papiſt, Browniſt, Anabaptiſt, nor Atheiſt, but a Proteſtant, and ſon of his Mother the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
